Preliminary Guide to the Talmadge Anderson Heritage House Collection of Audio-Visual Recordings 1949-2009
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Preliminary Guide to the Talmadge Anderson Heritage House Collection of Audio-Visual Recordings
1949-2009
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
UA 2023-02
Washington State University. Talmadge Anderson Heritage House
1 Linear foot of shelf space 1 Box
Audio/video recordings related to African-Americans and Washington State University or the northwest. They include academic presentations, musical performances.
WSU’s first African-American Heritage House was created in 1975, in the old Regional School Laboratory located adjacent to Cleveland Hall. In 1996 the center was renamed as the Talmadge Anderson Heritage House and moved into Cleveland Hall, and the old facility demolished. In 2007-2008 the university renovated three historic houses in the College Hill neighborhood, each for a different community of color: African/African Americans (Talmadge Anderson Heritage House (935 B St.)), Chicano/Latinos (Casa Latina (955 B St.)), and Native Americans (Native American Cultural House (975 B St.)). One for Asian/Pacific Islanders (Asian Pacific American Cultural House (905 C St.)) followed not too much later.
The Elson Floyd Cultural Center, opened in 2017, was planned to take the place of these four Heritage Houses, but no space was allocated for them in the final plans. The four houses were sold ca. 2020-2021, and their collections and holdings were repurposed or discarded.
The collection consists or recordings collected by or donated to the Talmadge Anderson Heritage House and those affiliated it with, over its history. The topics are related to African-Americans and Washington State University or the northwest. They include academic presentations, musical performances.
The CDs and DVDs have been copied to MASC archival storage.
This collection is open and available for research use.
After the WSU Heritage Houses were closed, the belongings of each house were collected by WSU for disposal. University Archivist Mark O’English went through each on Jan. 17th, 2023, and the materials here were among those selected for preservation due to their uniqueness and potential value as a historic record. They were initially retained as UA2023-02.
Among other materials salvaged from the Talmadge Anderson Heritage House were transcripts for materials held in the Black Oral History Interviews, 1972-1974 (CT 2) (added into that collections’ supporting material), slides from the filming of South by Northwest and from a goodbye presentation for Talmadge Anderson, a pair of busts of black pioneer legislator William Owen Bush, and the Washington State University Martin Luther King, Jr. Community Celebration Records, 1995-2020 (Archives 407)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University. Talmadge Anderson Heritage House -- Records and correspondence; Washington State University. Black Studies Program
African Americans -- Social conditions -- 20th century
African Americans; Washington (State); Colleges and Universities
- WSU Cultural Houses induction onto the National Historical register. CD/DVD., 2008-04-25
- Dedication of the Gladys Jennings Book Collection. CD/DVD., 2009-03-11
- AKA reception, second half. CD/DVD., 2006
- Office for Equity and Diversity. CD/DVD., 2006
- Women's Recognition Luncheon. CD/DVD., undated
- Women of Color Luncheon. CD/DVD., 2006-03
- Is Peace Possible? Gender and the Roots of War. Allan Johnson. CD/DVD., 2007-10-29
- Afro American Perspectives, #201 - Bussing. U-Matic., undated
- Northwest Black Pioneers. Bon Marche. VHS., 1994-02
- Democracy Matters. Cornel West. VHS., 2006-02-10
- Valuing Diversity. Jeff Guillory. VHS., 2002-10-10
- Elizabeth Cotton, Music of Black America. John Reid, Music 262. VHS., undated
- Afro American Perspective series, Reflections on African Art and Culture. VHS., undated
- Tribute to Black Composers. VHS., undated
- Race Matters. Corner West. VHS., undated
- Untangling the Knot of Racism. Allan Johnson. VHS., 2004-09-13
- Higher Education and the A.D.A. VHS., 1995-05-15
- Last Lecture series. Professor Young. VHS., 2006
- Music of Africa. Mbabi-Katana, in Kimbrough Hall. (4 reels). Audio reel-to-reel., 1969-03-26
- Dick Gregory (Note: He was on campus in Feb 73, so these are likely not his WSU visit.). Audio reel-to-reel., 1973-10-30
- Stokeley Carmichael. Audio reel-to-reel., undated
- Program #3. Black, Johnson, Anderson, Trim, Wilkins. Audio reel-to-reel., undated
- Black music - White People. Talmadge Anderson. Audio reel-to-reel., 1969-11-04
- Piano Solos. Art Tatum. Audio reel-to-reel., 1949-07-03
- Powell Barnett. Black History Project. Audio reel-to-reel., undated
- Jesse Jackson. Audio cassette., 1983-08
- Soul - South African entertainers. Letta Mbulu, Matiwante Manan, Keopetse, Willie Kgastitsile. Audio cassette., undated
- Night Sun. promotional. Audio cassette., undated
- Black Music 262. Pasco, WA. Sd1: B&B Restaurant, Butterball and the Vibratones. Sd2: Church of God in Christ. Audio cassette., undated
- Pasco, WA. Trinity Church of God in Christ. Audio cassette., 1971-05-16
- Pasco, WA. B&B Restaurant. Audio cassette., 1971-05-15
- Pasco Field Trip. Audio cassette., 1977-05-22
- ASALH Annual Meeting. Black Economics, Talmadge Anderson and one other presenter. Audio cassette., 1981-11-01
- Soul. Audio cassette., April 10.
- Terrel on Minority Studies. Audio cassette., undated